{"tossups": [{"question": "People affected by this phenomenon founded the Last Man Club, and one attempt to fix it was the Shelterbelt Project. This disaster was named in the aftermath of Black Sunday and was preceded by the\u201cgreat plow-up.\u201d Many individuals affected by this period\u2019s \u201cblack blizzards\u201d migrated along Route 66 to California\u2019s Central Valley, where they were branded as \u201cOkies\u201d. For ten points, name this ecological disaster during the Great Depression in which drought caused storms of topsoil across the southern Great Plains.", "answer": "<b> Dust Bowl</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Carl Peters\u2019 attempt to implement cotton quotas in this modern day country led to the Maji Maji Rebellion. The Chama Cha Mapinduzi party holds power in this country and was once led by a man who promoted \u201cujaama\u201d with the Arusha Declaration. The annexation of this country\u2019s Kagera province led this country to defeat and depose Idi Amin in neighboring Uganda. Julius Nyerere once led, for ten points, what African country formed in 1964 from the merger of Tanganyika and Zanzibar?", "answer": "<b> Tanzania</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During one of these events, a Cheyenne tribe killed a white buffalo and inscribed a peace treaty on its skin. A Roman tradition during one of these events involved a procession honoring the fertility god Priapus; that event is also known as the \u201cTears of Saint Lawrence.\u201d Giovanni Schiaparelli proved that one of these events is caused by a trail of debris from the Tempel-Tuttle comet entering Earth\u2019s atmosphere. The Perseids and Leonids are examples of, for ten points, what astronomical events in which streaks of light cross the sky?", "answer": "<b> meteor shower</b>s (accept<b> Leonid</b>s and/or<b> Perseid</b>s before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A popular myth about these people was promulgated by the Geatish Society during the early 19th century. Charles the Simple bought off these people with the Treaty of Saint-Clair-sur-Epte. These people were responsible for the destruction and looting of the Lindisfarne abbey in 793, and they raided much of Northern and Western Europe by traveling in longships. For ten points, name these Germanic people, whose rulers included Canute the Great, who were notorious for their pillaging.", "answer": "<b> Viking</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s 1974 Eurovision entry, \u201cAnd After the Farewell,\u201d was used by the MFA to signal the start of a revolution against Marcello Caetano. In that revolution, flowers were placed in gun barrels, as only four citizens of this country were killed as Antonio Salazar\u2019s Estado Novo was overthrown. For ten points, name this country, which granted independence to Angola and Mozambique in 1975, a year after the Carnation Revolution peacefully brought a military junta to power in Lisbon.", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This composer wrote the cantata<em> Gloria e Imeneo</em> for Louis XV\u2019s wedding and celebrated the defense of Corfu with the oratorio<em> Juditha triumphans</em>. Violas depict a barking sheepdog in one of his concertos, which was originally published with explanatory sonnets in<em> The Contest Between Harmony and Invention</em>. This violinst composed many of his works for a girl\u2019s orphanage in Venice and was known as the \u201cRed Priest.\u201d for ten points, name this Baroque composer who depicted Spring in his<em> Four Seasons</em>.", "answer": "Antonio<b> Vivaldi</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Stone slabs were harvested from this body of water by \u201cstonehookers\u201d in Port Credit and other towns. The Scarborough Bluffs lie on the northwest shore of this body of water, whose northeast was connected in 1832 by the Rideau Canal to the Ottawa River. The Niagara River connects this body of water to Lake Erie. Toronto lies on, for ten points, what smallest Great Lake by area, named for a Canadian province?", "answer": "Lake<b> Ontario</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Two men shared this award in 1997 for work on a formula used to calculate values for put and call options. Another winner of this award blamed inefficiencies in distribution for causing world hunger in his <em>Poverty and Famines</em>. In addition to Myron Scholes, Robert Merton, and Amartya Sen, this award has been won by Milton Friedman and 27 other University of Chicago thinkers. In 2008, Paul Krugman won, for ten points, what award, given annually in Sweden for work in a field that studies, among other things, consumption, production, and money?", "answer": "<b> Nobel</b> (Memorial) Prize in<b> Economics</b> (or Sveriges Riksbank Prize in<b> Economic</b> Science in Memory of Alfred <b>Nobel</b>; prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "One ruler of this name brought together the Ten Thousand under Xenophon to fight the broker of the Peace of Antalcidas, Artaxerxes II [art-ah-zerk-zees], his brother. An earlier ruler of this name was killed by the Massagetae [mass-ah-geh-tye] after he refused to marry Queen Tomyris. That ruler of this name disparaged Babylon\u2019s Nabonidus in an inscription on a clay cylinder and was buried in Pasargadae [pass-ar-gah-dye]. For ten points, give this name of a \u201cGreat\u201d ruler who founded the Achaemenid Dynasty in Persia.", "answer": "<b> Cyrus</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, the losing side briefly captured Fort Vaux. The winning side in this battle used rapid rotations, cycling in new troops to the front line every two weeks. Erich von Falkenhayn was removed as Chief of Staff after his failure to win this battle, though his goal of \u201cbleeding France white\u201dwas met with over 300,000 French casualties. Phillippe P\u2019etain ordered no retreat from, for ten points, what nine-month battle for a fortress complex in World War I?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Verdun</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In the aftermath of this event, its subject wrote that he was \u201cnow quite certain that the crimes of this guilty land will never be purged away.\u201d During this event, Matthew Ruppert survived being shot in the face during Israel Greene\u2019s attack on the engine house where hostages were being held. Robert E. Lee\u2019s marines ended this event, which sought to capture weapons in preparation for a slave revolt. For ten points, name this October 1859 event in which a federal arsenal was briefly seized by John Brown.", "answer": "Raid on<b> Harpers Ferry</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Max Hodel and Karl Nobiling attempted to assassinate one ruler from this house. Vincent, Count of Benedetti demanded that one prince of this house should reject offers to the Spanish throne, which were sensationalized in the Ems Dispatch. This house was overthrown in the November Revolution, leading to the establishment of the Weimar [VYE-mar] Republic. For ten points, name this German royal house that lost power after the abdication of Wilhelm II.", "answer": "House of<b> Hohenzollern</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Napoleon III was captured at the Battle of Sedan during this war.", "answer": "<b> Franco-Prussian</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One player for this team shared the 1997 MVP award with Brett Favre after rushing for 2,053 yards; that player retired in 1999, even though he was within 1,500 yards of Walter Payton\u2019s career rushing record. In 2010, another player for this team had a touchdown overruled for not maintaining possession for the entire catch under a controversial rule now named for him. For ten points, name this NFL team, whose lack of success under ownership by the Ford family caused Barry Sanders and Calvin Johnson to announce surprisingly early retirements.", "answer": "<b> Detroit Lions</b> (accept either)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Nearly 2,500 of these things were built in Carl Strandlund\u2019s factory in Columbus, Ohio, which was funded by the Reconstruction Finance Corporation; those things, named</b> <b>\u201cLustron,\u201d were made using enameled-steel that didn\u2019t require (+)</b> <b>painting.</b> <b>Levitt &</b> <b>Sons built over 17,000 of these things on Long Island, then discriminated against African-Americans by only selling or (*)</b> renting them to white families. For ten points, name these buildings, whose supply drastically increased after World War II to meet the demand of returning GIs and the Baby Boom.", "answer": "<b> house</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man signed the Belavezha Accords as one of his first acts in office, and he apologized for Korean Airlines Flight 007 after meeting with South Korean President Roh Tae-Woo. Bill Clinton claims that, in 1995, this foreign leader was found on the streets of D.C. calling</b> <b>for pizza while (+)</b> <b>drunk.</b> <b>A policy of economic \u201cshock therapy,\u201d suggested by Jeffrey</b> <b>Sachs, was implemented by this man in the (*)</b> 1990s. For ten points, name this first President of a post-Cold War Russia, who was responsible for ousting Mikhail Gorbachev in 1991.", "answer": "Boris<b> Yeltsin</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This author commented on Athenian inheritance laws in one play, in which Hypermnestra is unable to kill her husband after being instructed to do so. This author of the</b><em><b> Danaid </b></em><b>used Susa as the setting of a play about Xerxes\u2019s defeat at Salamis. He wrote about (+) Clytemnestra\u2019s killing of her husband and the ensuing revenge of Orestes in a prize-winning trilogy, and two of Oedipus\u2019s sons fight in this author\u2019s (*)</b><em> Seven Against Thebes</em>. For ten points, name this ancient Greek tragedian, the author of<em> The Persians</em> and the<em> Oresteia</em> trilogy.", "answer": "<b> Aeschylus</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Giulio Clovio landed this artist a job in Rome in the Palazzo Farnese, but he was later dismissed for being against the teachings of Michelangelo. His works were judged to not completely follow the rules of the Counter-Reformation, preventing him from working for</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Philip II. One of his works contrasts a dark and stormy sky with green hills and a</b> <b>cathedral spire, and in another, the (*)</b> clouds part to receive Don Gonzalo Ruiz. For ten points, name this Mannerist artist of<em> Burial of the Count of Orgaz</em> and<em> View of Toledo</em>, a Spanish artist from Crete.", "answer": "<b> El Greco</b> or Dom\u00b4enikos<b> Theotok\u00b4opoulos</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Pope Leo X owned one of these animals named Hanno, and a trader named Isaac helped procure one of these animals, named Abdul Abbas, for (+) Charlemagne. A marriage deal with Chandragupta Maurya gave the Seleucid Empire 500 of these animals, which served at the (*)</b> Battle of Ipsus. Spear lines were largely ineffective against the charge of these animals, due to their size. For ten points, name these pachyderms who also crossed the Alps with Hannibal.", "answer": "<b> elephant</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>The Vel\u2019 d\u2019Hiv [vell deev] Roundup in this city collected much of its Jewish population, and Marcel Petiot became notorious for strangling Jewish victims in this city during World War II. Only men were executed for treason by this city at Fort (+) Mont-Valerien. Albert Speer and Arno Breker toured this city with Hitler, who ordered General von Choltitz to burn it down after it was recovered by (*)</b> de Gaulle\u2019s Free French forces in 1944. For ten points, name this city where Hitler took a famous picture in front of the Eiffel Tower.", "answer": "<b> Paris</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The wife of Communist activist Luis Carlos Prestes, Olga Benario, was deported from this country to Nazi Germany. The Rua Tuonelero incident led to the suicide of one president of this country. This country\u2019s (+) \u201ccoffee and milk\u201d era of politics was dominated by the state of Minas Gerais [mee-nas zhair-ACE]. Slavery was abolished in this country by the (*)</b> Golden Law under Emperor Pedro II. Getulio Vargas once led, for ten points, what former Portuguese colony in South America?", "answer": "<b> Brazil</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}